Okay בוקר טוב *Boker Tov* everybody. Today's דף daf... *daf* is ל"ז
*Lamed Zayin*. We pick up at the bottom of ל"ו עמוד ב'
*Lamed Vav Amud Bet*. We had just finished a discussion in the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* about whether ניר *nir*, upturning, tilling the land,
overturning the soil, would be a חזקה chazakah. *chazakah*, but more significantly
at the end of the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*, it basically said that
the positions in the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael
*Rabbi Yishmael* and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva. *Rabbi Akiva*, that you can
have like a partial year in the beginning and a partial year
at the end, we have the statement of רב Rav ושמואל *Rav
and Shmuel* that that was only the opinion of רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* and רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael, *Rabbi Yishmael*, but the
חכמים Chachamim *Chachamim* say you need three full years,
and שמואל *Shmuel* says three full harvests, which quite possibly means less
than three years, but it still needs to be three full harvests.
Now before we continue, I wanted to read one important line from
the רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam* on that. If you take a look, the
רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam* says the following, he says, זו דברי רבי ישמעאל
Rabbi Yishmael, ורבי
עקיבא *Zu
divrei Rabbi Yishmael ve-Rabbi Akiva*. It is about twenty lines down in
the narrow lines, line starts with the word שנים *shanim*. Okay, and
then there's a two dots. זו דברי רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael ורבי
עקיבא *Zu divrei Rabbi Yishmael ve-Rabbi Akiva* he says דאמרינן במסכתין שדה
אחוזה חזקתה ג' שנים ואינו מיום ליום אלא י"ח חדשים לרבי ישמעאל
וי"ד לרבי עקיבא *de-amrinan be-masechtin s'deh achuzah chazakatah gimel shanim ve-eino miyom
leyom ela yud chet chodashim le-Rabbi Yishmael ve-yud daled le-Rabbi Akiva* אבל
חכמים Chachamim אומרים *aval chachamim omrim* line starting with the word חכמים
*chachamim* in the narrow lines of the רשב"ם Rashbam. *Rashbam* about exactly
in the middle. אבל חכמים אומרים חזקתם ג' שנים בכל דבר מיום
ליום ועליבא דהני רבנן Rabanan פרישנא בריש פרקין טעמא דחזקת ג' שנים
דעד ג' שנים מזדהר איניש בשטריה דכוותיה דהני רבנן Rabbanan אליבא דרב
קאימה *aval chachamim omrim chazakatam shalosh shanim be-chol davar miyom leyom ve-aliba
de-hanei rabanan parishna be-reish pirkin ta'ama de-chazakat gimel shanim de-ad shalosh shanim
mizdehar inish bishatarei de-kvasei de-hanei rabanan aliba de-rav ka'ima*. So what he
says is like this. He says, he connects the debate of the
חכמים *Chachamim* and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* and רבי ישמעאל
Rabbi Yishmael *Rabbi Yishmael* to the question of how does חזקה chazakah
*chazakah* work? You might remember in the beginning of the פרק perek,
*perek*, there's two opinions about how חזקה chazakah *chazakah* works. One is
you do something three times and it sort of creates a status
change, it establishes you in that sort of position, which was a
little funny because how do you actually make a legitimate claim, but
it was the doing it of three times that established your status
and identity.
The other approach was שור מועד *shor mu'ad*.
The other approach was no, after three years you have a legitimate
reason why you don't have a שטר shtar. *shtar*. So the רשב"ם
Rashbam *Rashbam* says, well, how do you explain the position, there's a
debate here, do you need three full years or can it be
like three harvests or you know, partial years? So he says well,
if it's about שור מועד *shor mu'ad* and doing something three times
and changing a status, maybe it could be three harvests, maybe it
could be a partial year at the beginning and a partial year
at the end. But if it's about losing your שטר shtar. *shtar*
and when you have a legitimate claim hey, I lost my שטר
shtar. *shtar*, that has to do with calendar time, so that means
three full years. So the רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam* connects that to those
two to this debate to that debate. Other ראשונים *Rishonim* disagree. For
example, the נימוקי יוסף *Nimukei Yosef* says give me a break, you
know, all along the, he doesn't say give me a break, all
along, all along the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* has on the one hand
been assuming the issue is that you don't pay attention to your
שטר *shtar*, and at the same time assuming that חזקה chazakah *chazakah*
is only meaningful based on doing types of things that make you
look like the owner and that would provoke a response from the
original owner. So he says these are not independent things. It's not
like just the pure passage of time makes me less responsible with
my שטר *shtar*. What makes me less responsible with my שטר *shtar*
is I've been acting in this way that demonstrates me as the
owner for such a long time and nobody has said anything, so
now I figure nobody's going to complain anymore and that allows me
to, so it's not just calendar time. So we can both embrace
the idea about not being careful with your שטר *shtar* and say
it's not just a function of straight amount of calendar time. That
it interrelates with the idea of the silence of the owner, his
silence is an indication that I own it, the fact that I
did provoke things that could have provoked him and he didn't say
anything and he didn't respond, that gives me a legitimate reason not
to be careful with my שטר *shtar*. So being careful with your
שטר *shtar* does not necessarily translate into a fixed amount of calendar
time. Okay, so I just wanted to sort of show us how
this issue, the two basic models that we had, how do they
interplay with the question of is חזקה chazakah *chazakah* about three harvests
and is it measured by things that will provoke the owner or
is it measured by pure calendar time? And the רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam*
tries to sort of make them sort of, you know, one-to-one correspondence
between those two conceptual approaches and two ways of measuring the time.
And other ראשונים *Rishonim* say no, the issue about careful with your
שטר *shtar* is not just about calendar time, it's about the type
of response or lack of response of the owner and the types
of things you're doing that would evoke those responses or not. Yes.
So the נימוקי יוסף *Nimukei Yosef*, if I'm understanding this correctly, would
be potentially have an even further compressed time period if you did
something outrageously outlandish provocative in, right?
Well maybe, but for example, that might be
שמואל *Shmuel*. שמואל *Shmuel* says that... Okay, so now let's continue in
the גמרא. Gemara The גמרא Gemara. says the following. אמר רבי ישמעאל,
Amar Rabbi Yishmael, okay, במה דברים אמורים בשדה לבן. Bamei devarim amurim
bisdei lavan. Now talking about alternatives to three full years, the last
opinion of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael in the משנה is that this
is all about a wheat field, but if it's about a type
of an orchard, he even goes so far to say that you
can get three harvests within one year of three different types of
trees, right? You get one, bring in the grapes, bring in the
olives, bring in the, what was the other thing? The, I forget,
and ta-da,
and oh, bring in the grain he says, but it's not grain,
no, because the רשב"ם Rashbam says it means wine. Bring in the
wine, bring in the olives and bring in the, oh, and bring
in the dates, I guess.
He claims שדה לבן S'deh Lavan means orchard, I'm just going to...
No, שדה לבן S'deh Lavan is the opposite. שדה לבן S'deh Lavan
is a wheat field because you look at it, it's all white.
Okay. And say when is this true? It's true by a wheat
field, but if you're dealing with an orchard, then you don't even
need three, something that represents three calendar years, three different harvests count.
So if you have different types of trees in your orchard and
you bring in one time the dates that have been drying out
in the field or the figs that have been drying out and
then the grapes and then the olives, all in the same year,
that's a חזקה. chazakah So there, really it's not about calendar time.
So let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. אמר אביי, Amar
Abaye, מדרבי ישמעאל נשמע לרבנן. Miderabbi Yishmael nishma lerabanan. From רבי ישמעאל,
Rabbi Yishmael even though we said now we don't פסקן pasken like
רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael there's a position of the חכמים that you
really need three years and not three partial years and not three
harvests in the same year, but nevertheless, there's something about this that's
relevant for the רבנן's Rabbanan position. What is that? היינו שלושים אילנות
ממטע עשרה לבית סאה. Hayinu shloshim ilanot mimateh asarah l'veit se'ah. You
have thirty trees planted in a בית סאה, Beit Se'ah, oh excuse
me, you have thirty trees distributed over a plot of land in
the ratio of ten trees to a בית סאה. Beit Se'ah. You
might remember that, right? We dealt with that before, that there's a
sense that a בית סאה, Beit Se'ah, a field fifty by fifty,
the proper sort of distribution of trees there is ten trees to
that amount. So you have thirty trees planted in a field with
the proper type of distribution, it's not seen as overcrowded. We'll actually
get in a minute to questions about being overcrowded. And what did
you do? אכל עשרה בשנה זו ועשרה בשנה זו ועשרה בשנה זו.
Achal asarah b'shanah zo v'asarah b'shanah zo v'asarah b'shanah zo. Now you
did not go ahead, you were there for three full years because
we're rejecting רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael. and רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva You
need three full years. Okay, but each year you harvested, but you
didn't harvest all thirty each year. Each year you harvested ten of
the thirty. הרי זו חזקה. Harei zo chazakah. That works. How do
you learn it out from רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael in the following
way? לאו מי אמר רבי ישמעאל, Lav mi amar Rabbi Yishmael, didn't
רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael say, what? For the whole בית סאה? Beit
Se'ah? Didn't, no, it's more than a בית סאה, Beit Se'ah, it's
three בית סאהs. Beit Se'ahs. Didn't רבי ישמעאל say for the whole
area? Didn't רבי ישמעאל say חד פירא הוי חזקה לכולהו פירי? Chad
peira havei chazakah l'chulhu peiri? He says think about רבי ישמעאל. You
did three things, three harvests, but each harvest only related to part
of your area, part of your field, right? You brought in the
grapes. The grapes were only distributed in a third of the field.
That counts as one harvest of the field. Then you brought in
the figs. The figs only came from a third of the field,
but that represents a second harvest of the entire field. Then you
brought in the, what was the other thing? The olives. The olives
are only planted in a third of the field, but that represents
a חזקה chazakah on the entire field. So even though we don't
go like רבי ישמעאל that a harvest counts as a year, you
need three full years, we shouldn't reject the implicit assumption that he
says that when you harvest from part of the field, it counts
as a חזקה chazakah for the whole field. Okay, so that's what
he says. לאו מי אמר רבי ישמעאל חד פירא הוי חזקה לכולהו
פירי, Lav mi amar Rabbi Yishmael chad peira havei chazakah l'chulhu peiri,
that one fruit, harvesting one set of fruit counts for all the
fruit of the field. הכי נמי הני הוי חזקה להני והני הוי
חזקה להני. Hachi nami hanei havei chazakah lahanei v'hanei havei chazakah lahanei.
Harvesting from some of the trees count for all the trees and
vice versa or in the same by the others.
Now the גמרא Gemara says, sounds like a very good fruit. Why
not? Because maybe the רבי ישמעאל would only say what he says
if at that time only that fruit is available.
Ah, very good. So maybe
it only works with the other things if it's not a conscious
leaving over of the,
if you have the opportunity to harvest thirty and you're only harvesting
ten, that's very different than if this is the only harvest available
right now. Excellent. So that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to
say. You anticipated the גמרא. Gemara והני מילי היכא דלא אפיקי. V'hanei
mili heicha d'lo afiki. Look at the next line of the גמרא.
Gemara, I'm going to believe that you did not read ahead. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says, והני מילי היכא דלא אפיקי, V'hanei mili
heicha d'lo afiki, that's only if the other stuff has not yet
produced its fruit. So that it works in the same way, that
when you're harvesting ten of the trees, that those are the only
trees that are available to be harvested. אבל אפיקי ולא אכלינהו לא
הוי חזקה. Aval afiki v'lo achlinhu lo havei chazakah. But if they
have produced their fruit and you're not eating them, you're not harvesting
them, then you're like explicitly leaving, abandoning them, that doesn't work. It
works if they're... this is what is available to harvest right now.
Then the גמרא Gemara says also והוא דבזי ביזוי, vehu debazei bizuyei,
and it's also if the trees are equally distributed. If the trees
are like, you know, so it's if if there's like,
right, if this is your field and here you have ten trees
and here you have ten trees and here you have ten trees,
right, and for whatever reason they're at different stages of ripeness.
So one year you harvest this, one year you harvest this and
one year you harvest this, then this does not represent the entire
field. This is its own plot, this is its own plot, this
is its own plot. So that won't work. It only works if
your trees are like randomly distributed, which is not, which does not
make for efficient farming because then, you know, you have to move
all around to do it. But if, you know, if your trees
are distributed like so these are one set of trees, right, and
these are the other and
this
is another set and like that, and you know, it looks like
this, right, then you understand, right, so when you do either all
the purples or all the browns or all the oranges or whatever,
you're doing it represents, right, the entire field. Of course, that's very
inefficient farming. You'd want to have the trees that ripen at the
same time like clustered together. Okay, but anyway, that's the way the
גמרא Gemara is applying, which also means to assume that, which the
רשבם Rashbam says but it's hard to believe, that your vines are
interspersed with your olive trees which are interspersed with your, you know,
with your figs. First of all, they're כלאים. kilayim. Second of all,
it's highly inefficient. So I don't exactly get the analogy of the
גמרא, Gemara but you understand that the גמרא Gemara wants to limit
this idea because it doesn't really make sense if it's in all
in a separate plot that one plot should work for the other
plot.
Wait, so this limiting of דבזי ביזוי debazei bizuyei
is what? What are they limiting?
That this only works that doing ten trees represents the חזקה chazakah
for the whole field if those ten trees are distributed throughout the
whole field. But if these ten are in one section and those
ten are in another and those ten are in another, then doing
a חזקה chazakah on one set of trees means nothing for the
rest of the field.
What about the idea that the whole field was producing fruit but
you've only harvested from one section? How is that related to this
idea?
That's exactly the point. That's why if you only harvest from one
section, it doesn't count for the rest of the sections. That's why
it only works if these ten trees are distributed, if everything is
interspersed.
And that's בזי דבזוי? bazei debazuyei?
Yeah, בזי ביזוי bazei bizuyei somehow means לשון בזיע, lashon beziah, split
or cracked or whatever. In any event, so it means that these
ten are
פיזור, pizur, says the רשבם. Rashbam So if the trees of the
different years are interspersed and scattered out, then any ten of them,
when you do those ten of this year, it's doing it on
the entire field. But if they're in their own section, it's only
doing it on its section, it's not doing it on the entire
field.
But if they're spread
out, the
פיזור pizur throughout the
whole field, you harvest them then that's a גילוי דעת giluy da'at
that the whole place belongs to you.
I wouldn't necessarily use the word גילוי דעת, giluy da'at, but then
that is a חזקה chazakah that is on the entire place.
Yes. But גילוי דעת giluy da'at is a גילוי. giluy. Really? It's
מגלה, megaleh, you're מגלה megaleh that it's not yours. Huh?
What do you mean?
I don't know where he's saying that, but you'll find that language
for me. Yes, Michael.
Okay, so but let's say it's, you said that's for a בית
סאה, beit se'ah, let's say it's over ארבעה בית סאה arba'ah beit
se'ah and that's the whole field.
Yeah, so we'll get to that because there's always this question about
what's considered to be the trees that are connected to a certain
amount of space. So if the space is larger, then this amount
of trees doesn't relate to a larger space, it only relates to,
you know, the theme, like the ten trees to the בית סאה
beit se'ah is those are a connected unit.
But if the whole field is ארבעה בית סאה arba'ah beit se'ah
then and so only getting three limit...
Yeah, well, that's in general true also. If you're harvesting trees and
it's a very large area, then you don't necessarily have a חזקה
chazakah on all of the ground. You might have a חזקה chazakah
on the trees but not all the ground because the whole ground
is not seen as intimately connected to the trees.
Except then the owner comes back then and says, "Look, then this
guy is believed to own the trees..."
Right, imagine. I've got this big plot of land, you've got some
trees like this widely spread out, you are harvesting these trees, but
there's all of this wide open space here that's seen as not
necessarily needed for the trees and not connected to the trees. You
want a חזקה chazakah, on this space here, you've got to do
something on it. So therefore you need there to
be...
maybe have a חזקה chazakah on the trees. Right, exactly. And that's
actually going to turn to right now. So that's why you want
there to be the right ratio between the tree and the land,
because that ratio is understood to be where the land is needed
for the trees and that creates like this whole orchard identity and
therefore harvesting the trees works on the entire orchard. But if it's
spread out over large space, then it's just random trees in a
big field and the trees, you know, harvesting the trees isn't a
חזקה chazakah. on the field. Charlie.
There are discussions in חז"ל Chazal about what constitutes a vineyard as
opposed to a vine here.
Right, well, we're actually getting to all of that. So let's take
a look. Yes, very quickly here because you guys are not going
to let me go forward.
Okay, so דף...
Yes, Friday the second segment. I know, I know Charlie. Yes.
היכא דאכל כל הפירות גילה על עצמו שהשדה נעשית כטיפול. Heicha d'achal
kol hapeirot gila al atzmo shehasadeh naaseit k'tipul. גילוי, giluy, right?
I mean, yeah, but I wouldn't call it גילוי דעת. giluy da'at.
גילוי דעת Giluy da'at means it, yeah, correct. גילוי דעת Giluy da'at
means you're revealing your intention. גילה על עצמו Gila al atzmo means
your actions demonstrate the facts about what, anyway, I don't want to
belabor it. Okay, let's go on. זה החזיק באילנות וזה החזיק בקרקע.
Zeh hechezik b'ilanot v'zeh hechezik b'karka.
Now,
let's say
Charlie here used to own this orchard, okay? And now over the
last three years,
David has been harvesting the fruit off of the orchard and Gennevair
has been
working the land of the orchard, planting her own things or doing
something directly on the land, not just on the tree. For three
years. What? Planting anything? No, she's harvesting, okay? She's, I don't know
what she's doing. She's planting a vegetable garden and she's harvesting. Okay,
so anyway, alright, so that's what you got going on this plot
of land that had trees that originally was owned by Charlie. So,
אמר רב זביד, זה קנה אילנות וזה קנה קרקע. amar Rav Zevid
zeh kanah ilanot vezeh kanah karka. Now, because he uses the language
קנה, kanah, you might remember there was a גמרא Gemara earlier that
used that language, which meant it's a חזקה chazakah, that works for
the trees, it's a חזקה chazakah. that works for the קרקע, karka,
and that's the way תוספות Tosafot reads it. But I do want
to take a step back and say the רשב״ם Rashbam reads קנה
kanah here literally. The רשב״ם Rashbam does not read the scenario the
way I just described it. The רשב״ם Rashbam reads it that Charlie
basically went to his two good friends David and Jenna and said,
Hey guys, I really don't use this plot of land here, I'm
going to give it to you, okay? I'm going to sell it
to you or I'm going to give it to you as a
gift, I'm going to give David the trees and I'm going to
give Jenna the land. And they went and the word החזיק hechezik
he reads means did חזקה, chazakah, not a חזקה chazakah. of three
years, did an act of taking possession, okay? David watered the trees,
Jenna tilled the land, and it was not three years, just one
act. And now the question is, Charlie was a little vague because
he said, I'm giving David the trees and Jenna the land. Now
did you give David just the trees or did you give him
the land under the trees? What happens if those trees get cut
down? Is he able to replant that land underneath them? That's not
clear. Did you give him any other land associated with the trees?
So that's what the רשב״ם Rashbam says. The question is, so the
word החזיק hechezik is really immaterial here. It could have been they
paid money for it or something. The question is, what was Charlie's
intent when he split it between the two of you? תוספות Tosafot
says no, no, no, we're talking here about חזקה. chazakah But it's
still related because the גמרא Gemara is going to relate it to
this question of when somebody sells, how do we decide if they're
selling the land with the trees or not? So even though it's
about חזקה, chazakah it's related to this question. Because now it's a
case of חזקה. chazakah David's been working the trees for three years,
Jenna's been working the land for three years, it originally was Charlie's.
They're going to each claim they own it. How much is their
act of חזקה, chazakah what does it represent that they own? And
this is very tied in, right? If you work ten trees scattered
out, does it represent you own the whole space? Right, we just
got through discussing if it's a very large plot of land and
you work the ten trees, it doesn't represent that you own the
whole land, it's only a small plot of land connected to the
trees. Okay, so if David is working the trees and Jenna is
working the land, what does his working the tree for three years,
what should we understand what type of ownership is it implicitly representing?
How much does it include the land or not? Jenna, obviously it
includes the land, not the trees, but David's working of the trees,
how much does it imply or represent that he owns the land
that goes with it? So for that, the question would be, well,
what would we imagine would be the case if Charlie sold the
land and said, I'm giving David the trees and Jenna the land?
What would we assume that David would own? So in the end,
it sort of collapses to the same question. When you sell and
split it and give one guy the tree and one guy the
land, how much do we assume the guy who got the tree
got it with the land or without the land? But at least
תוספות Tosafot says the starting point is חזקה. chazakah So David's working
the trees, Jenna's working the land, we want to understand what does
it represent that they own, and that would be the way we
would say, well, what does David's trees, does it show that he
owns the land or not show he owns the land? Well, what
would it have meant if Charlie would have given him the trees
or sold him the trees? Would that have come with the land
or not? And that's a way of interpreting what his חזקה chazakah
on the trees means. Yes.
So I want to understand this. You said these trees are just,
the land Jenna's working is on like let's say the north side
and the trees...
No, no, no, they're together. They're not separate.
Oh, so this is interspersed.
Yeah, he's got these trees, he's harvesting these trees, Jenna's planting the
land, and we want to know, does David own the actual little
plot of land that the trees are on and therefore if the
tree dries up he'll be able to replant it?
Or even like ארבע אמות, arba amot, right? Because my trees are
getting nutrients from... It's possible he owns say it says י"ב אמות.
yud bet amot.
So there's a lot of possibilities. It's possible he owns absolutely none
of the land, he just has the right to have his tree
there and if the tree dries up he has to leave. It's
possible he owns say it says י"ב אמות. yud bet amot. It's
possible he owns... you know, there's all these different ways of determining
how much land is associated with the tree. But all he's been
doing is harvesting the fruit. So how much does the harvesting of
the fruit show he owns any part of the land?
Wait, so I'm trying to understand, if he actually owns the land,
then can he kick Jenna off from...
No, Jenna clearly also owns the land. And how did he... So
then they would have to figure out which part does he get,
which part does she get? Maybe he only gets this. Okay, but
that's the question. First let's determine if it represents any part of
the land and then we'll determine how to divide it between him
and Jenna.
Okay, so let's say something like a university owns the land but
not the building? Something like that.
Yeah, I mean it's... that's the question. Okay, so let's take a
look.
What about his rights in terms of passage in terms to get
to...
that's a separate issue, but that's also a good question. Okay. זה
החזיק באילנות וזה החזיק בקרקע. zeh hechezik ba'ilanot vezeh hechezik bakarka. אמר
רב זביד Amar Rav Zevid, זה קנה אילנות וזה קנה קרקע. zeh
kanah ilanot v'zeh kanah karka. So I'm going to read it like
תוספות Tosafot where קנה kanah does... where it means this one's חזקה
chazakah, only represents ownership of trees and does not represent any ownership
of the land and the other one's חזקה chazakah represents ownership of
the land. מתקיף לה רב פפא. matkif lah Rav Pappa. Now רב
פפא Rav Pappa challenges. אם כן אין לו לבעל אילנות בקרקע כלום.
im ken ein lo lebaal ilanot bakarka klum. So you're telling me
that the guy who has the trees has absolutely no ownership of
the land? לימא ליה בעל קרקע לבעל אילנות, leima leh baal karka
lebaal ilanot, so if that's true, Jenna could just say to David,
עקור אילנך שקול
וזיל, akor ilnach shekol vezil, uproot your tree, take it and leave.
Okay. Now, the question is, so the answer as רשב"ם Rashbam might
say is, yes, that is correct. That is exactly what I am
saying. You have properly understood my position. So רב פפא Rav Pappa
is not contradicting רב זביד, Rav Zevid, he's just saying like I
can't believe that. I cannot accept that, you know, something that is
demonstrating ownership of the tree should be interpreted to mean no ownership
of the land. Now, the question is he's doing a reductio ad
absurdum. Is he saying that according to you, you know, Jenna could
tell David today take your tree out of here, you have no
rights to it? That would seem like a real reductio ad absurdum,
hard to imagine that רב זביד Rav Zevid would say that. So
mostly רשב"ם Rashbam and תוספות Tosafot think that what he means is
he's still saying look, you know, when you tell me that as
soon as David's tree would dry up, if it got chopped down
or whatever, that he wouldn't be able to replant it? That's crazy.
Now, of course, that's not so crazy. Okay. So it depends how
much he's... how much he's reducing ad absurdum, right? Either he's saying
like if you take what you said to its logical conclusion, you
know, he would be forced to uproot his trees today and רב
זביד Rav Zevid might say I'm not saying that. He has rights
as long as the tree is there, but just once the tree
isn't there, he doesn't... then he doesn't have rights to stay there.
But either way, right, he can't plant after the tree... after the
tree is cut down and whatever. Okay, but nevertheless רב פפא Rav
Pappa does not like this. רב פפא Rav Pappa thinks if David's
got the trees, he must have some land that goes with the
trees. He doesn't just have
the trees and rights while the tree is there, he must really
have some land. So how much land? Right, so how much? אלא
אמר רב פפא זה קנה אילנות וחצי קרקע וזה קנה חצי קרקע.
ela amar Rav Pappa zeh kanah ilanot vechatzi karka vezeh kanah chatzi
karka. So David has the trees and half of the plot of
land and Jenna has only half. Once he has land, it represents...
the taking the חזקה chazaka. on the tree represents a חזקה chazakah.
on the entire plot. So he and Jenna are competing for חזקות
chazakot on the entire plot and it's considered to be half and
half. Now, that seems a little bit of an extreme in the
other direction and the רשב"ם Rashbam actually says maybe it's לאו דווקא.
lav davka. Maybe he doesn't really mean half. Maybe he means the
immediate space underneath the tree, some immediate area around the tree. Maybe
it doesn't literally mean half. Okay, it says half, but he... it's
a little bit too much of a swing in the opposite direction
and he tries to pull it back a little bit. Jenna you
had a question? Okay.
So but they can't plant different trees, let's say the roots go
further out, right?
Yeah, it's only... well, that's the question. How much of half is
meant... means half.
No, no, I'm assuming it is. Yeah. What? Meaning like, you know,
like if you say that, right, then again, like if you come
to that conclusion, then I can't, even though I'm on my half,
the roots are going to go into your half then I can't
like, you know, plant... plant something that... whose roots are going to
extend into your area.
Yeah, I don't know, maybe. Okay, I can't... I can't get to
that right now. Now the גמרא Gemara says like this, פשיטא מכר
קרקע ושייר אילנות לפניו יש לו קרקע. pishita machar karka veshayar ilanot
lefanav yesh lo karka. Now, now because this issue, even if we
assume תוספות Tosafot that what is going on here is a classic
חזקה chazakah which makes sense, how we interpret the חזקה, chazakah as
I said before, what does taking the חזקה chazakah on the tree
represent? How much ownership of קרקע? karka? To some degree, it would
be linked to what do we think would happen if somebody would
sell David the trees? Would it go with the קרקע karka or
not? Okay, now, one of the things that you need to know
is, and תוספות Tosafot and the רשב"ם Rashbam spend a lot of
time, which is why there's so little words on this page, trying
to make this work with another גמרא Gemara because another classic גמרא
Gemara is I own this plot of land and I'm going to
sell to Jenna the trees. If I sell Jenna two
trees... she doesn't really get any land outside of the space of
the trees. If I sell her three trees, then she gets a
plot of land that is sort
of that the trees are in and there's a question of exactly
how to define its parameters. So the question is why is that
not exactly what's being discussed here? It all depends on two or
three and so on. Why are we not bringing that discussion in
here?
And the basic issue is somebody got the land.
Exactly. Thank you very much David. So the point is if I
am selling to Jenna and I'm holding back the stuff for myself
and selling to Jenna then we might say well I'm holding back
as much land as possible for myself you know or there's a
default assumption that I'm giving her
less like I'm not being overly generous where the phrase in the
גמרא Gemara's is used מוכר בעין רעה הוא מוכר. mocher b'ayin ra'ah
hu mocher. Okay we don't assume I'm being overly generous when I'm
selling it. But if I'm divesting myself of the entire property and
I'm selling it to David and Jenna and I'm dividing it between
them then maybe since I'm not holding anything back for myself maybe
I'm giving David a certain amount of land with those trees more
than he would get if he were just buying the trees from
me and I was holding the land back for myself.
Like מוכר בעין יפה? mocher b'ayin yaffah?
Well yes but here you don't have to say יפה yaffah רעה
ra'ah because I'm fully divesting myself of the land. So the question
isn't how much am I holding back for myself it's how I'm
splitting it between David and Jenna. So when I sell just the
trees to David I might hold back all the land for myself.
But when I fully divest myself of the land maybe David is
going to get some of the land to go with the trees.
So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says like this
פשיטא מכר קרקע ושייר אילנות. pishita machar karkah v'shayar ilanos. So now
we are going to deal though before we get to two purchasers
which is what's unique about this case we're going to go back
to a classic case of one seller and one buyer. Okay? But
rather than me selling the trees what I'm actually doing is I'm
keeping the trees for myself and I'm selling the land. Okay? So
the גמרא Gemara says it's פשיטא pishita it's obvious מכר קרקע machar
karkah you sold the land ושייר אילנות לפניו v'shayar ilanos lefanav and
you kept the possession of the trees. יש לו קרקע yesh lo
karkah then I retain possession of the land which is meaning what?
Hold on let me just check the רשב"ם Rashbam says here. Hold
on. Oh
I'm sorry right I have possession of the land that is needed
for the trees. Okay? Right.
So the purchaser of the trees gets some land.
No no no it's not the purchaser the purchaser of the land.
I own the whole land with the trees. I am selling the
land to Jenna there. She's interested in land as we saw from
the last story. I keep for my trees even if it's only
one or two trees. If I sell one or two trees the
buyer doesn't get any land with it. But here it's the reverse.
I'm selling the land and I'm keeping the trees. And even if
they're only one or two since I'm the original owner and they're
my trees we're going to presume that I'm going to keep some
land that goes with the trees that are needed for the trees.
So יש לו קרקע yesh lo karkah doesn't mean all the קרקע.
karkah. It means קרקע karkah immediately around the trees that is needed
for the trees. מכר קרקע ושייר אילנות לפניו. machar karkah v'shayar ilanos
lefanav. So you sold the land and you held back the trees.
יש לו קרקע yesh lo karkah you have land that goes with
the trees a certain amount. We're not going to worry now how
much. ואפילו לרבי עקיבא דאמר מוכר בעין יפה הוא מוכר v'afilu l'Rabbi
Akiva d'amar mocher b'ayin yaffah hu mocher even according to רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva who says that when you sell something to someone we
assume generous terms of the sale. So for example one example about
this is and this gets back to whoever was asking the question
about access let's say I go ahead and I sell somebody
a well in my field. And then he buys the well. And
then he says great I want to go to my well. And
I say no I didn't sell you a path. You want to
get to your well go fly. That's not my responsibility. Oh you
want access to the well? That'll cost you extra right? So that's
מוכר בעין רעה הוא מוכר. mocher b'ayin ra'ah hu mocher. Whereas if
you say מוכר בעין יפה הוא מוכר mocher b'ayin yaffah hu mocher
we assume if you're selling the well you're also selling access to
the well and other types of questions. Other types of issues where
do we assume you also sold a certain amount of other things
that were necessary for the reasonable use of this object or do
we only interpret what you sold in the most limited terms בעין
רעה הוא מוכר או בעין יפה הוא מוכר? b'ayin ra'ah hu mocher
o b'ayin yaffah hu mocher? So even according to רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva. who says מוכר בעין יפה הוא מוכר mocher b'ayin yaffah hu
mocher so here we go I sold all this קרקע karkah to
Jenna. Why don't I say I sold her all the קרקע karkah
and I didn't leave for myself any land? I only left for
myself the trees and she owns every single inch of land right
up to the trees. No we wouldn't say that. Even according to
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva. who says מוכר בעין יפה הוא מוכר mocher
b'ayin yaffah hu mocher הני מילי גבי בור ודות. hani mili gabi
bor v'dos. That is if I basically am selling somebody a you
know a what do you call it a
hold on yeah I just want to check רשב"ם Rashbam make sure
I'm getting the directions right one minute.
Right so the classic case of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva. is
like I said one minute hold on.
Right. So,
oh, okay, okay, okay. So here's the other case for רבי עקיבא.
Rabbi Akiva Not the case of I'm selling you access to my
well. Let me, let's say it the other way. Let's say I
went ahead, and this is very similar to the case of the
trees. I sold you my house. I'm selling you my house, my
plot of land, but I said to you, Jenna, I'm selling you
the house and the land and everything but I still own the
well. Okay, fine. Good. I still own the well. Then I sell
it all to Jenna. Now I want to go to my well.
Now Jenna says to me the same thing. She says, oh, you
want to go to your well? That'll cost you. Okay, that was
מוכר בעין יפה הוא מוכר. mocher b'ayin yaffa hu mocher. I sold
her everything, I retained ownership of the well, I didn't I'm assuming
even in my to my own detriment that I did not retain
access rights to that well. I know, but that's מוכר בעין יפה.
mocher b'ayin yaffa. I gave her everything that was coming, everything. So
if we're going to say that by the well that I didn't
retain access rights to the well, then why are we going to
say that I retained the land around the trees? If I'm so
willing even when I give it to somebody else and even when
I'm retaining for myself, I hurt my own self-interest when it's מוכר
בעין יפה, mocher b'ayin yaffa, so why is the trees different than
the well? Because well, that's the position of רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva
So we'll see that when we get to it. ואפילו רבי עקיבא
דאמר מוכר בעין יפה מוכר, v'afilu Rabbi Akiva d'amar mocher b'ayin yaffa
mocher, even when we say you're very generous and you don't retain
anything for yourself more than exactly what you said, הני מילי לגבי
בור ודות, hani mili lgabi bor v'dous, that's by by like a
well and a cistern דלא מחשי בארעא, d'lo machshi b'ara, that their
presence do not hurt the land. So therefore, right, meaning think of
it from Jenna's perspective. If Jenna could plant right up to the
edge of the well, right? And the and the fact that I
own the well, the fact that I own the well, that doesn't
encroach onto her space. So it doesn't it doesn't weaken the ground,
the ground is usable right up to the well. So if if
you were to Jenna to give her anything less any to take
away anything from that land would actually be hurting Jenna's interests. And
since I am assumed to be very generous, I'm going to give
her every single square inch up to the well because my well
does not encroach at all onto her land and I'm going to
maximize what she got. דלא מחשי בארעא. d'lo machshi b'ara. אבל אילנות,
aval ilanos, but by the tree, I'm selling her the land and
I'm keeping the tree, דקמחשי בארעא. d'kamachshi b'ara. So the presence of
my tree, right? So if here's my plot of land that I
just sold to Jenna, and here's my here's the well, okay? So
Jenna can so I would like some access to that well. But
if I'm keeping for myself access to that well, I'm taking away
space that Jenna could use. Let's say I just even want like
a little standing space around that well. But that's space that Jenna
could use because Jenna could plant every single square inch. So therefore,
since it's מוכר בעין יפה הוא מוכר, mocher b'ayin yaffa hu mocher,
I don't want to take away any usable space from Jenna. So
she has every single square inch and I just have the well.
And if I want access to it, I'll have to pay for
it. That's רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva But if this, rather than being
a well, were a tree, okay? So then Jenna can't plant right
up to the tree, or not reasonably, because the area right around
the tree where the roots go is area where it the presence
of the roots makes it not so usable land for planting, right?
So in that type of a case, because the natural situation is
one that A, I need the area, but I needed the area
by the well. Okay, so needing it isn't enough. But B, the
area is not really so usable by the other person, then it's
assumed that I did retain for myself because I didn't really hurt
them by retaining it for myself. Okay, so let's take a read.
In that case, דקמחשי בארעא, d'kamachshi b'ara, that actually is injuring the
land around it, שיורי שייר, shiyurei shiyer, you did leave it for
yourself.
And some seem to say that it's to protect the owner of
the
tree, ואי לא, v'ei lo, let's read that, that's also the next
line. ואי לא שייר, v'ei lo shiyer, because if he didn't leave
it for himself,
לימא ליה, leima lei, according think also about the alternative. If in
the case of the well, okay, Jenna can't take me tell me
fill up your well. She can charge me for access to it,
but I still have full rights to my well, full ownership. In
this case, if Jenna actually owned this land, right? Then she would
say to me, like going back to remember the second פרק, perek,
that when my tree is is going into your land, she would
say to me, hey Dov, your roots are going into my land.
You gotta go ahead and do something about that. So by if
so my giving her that would actually undermine, jeopardize my ownership of
the tree itself. All right, so that that far we won't go.
So to give to give her up to every single square inch
up to the בור, bor, okay, it doesn't jeopardize my ownership of
the
בור. bor. Demand any space around it would encroach on her rights
and would jeopardize and, okay, on the one hand, to take away
would encroach, and B, have, and B, not giving her all the
land doesn't jeopardize my ownership of the well. It jeopardizes my access,
but it doesn't jeopardize my ownership, right? There's two different things, whereas
here, here, there are two reasons why to retain the land. Number
one, my, the land around it doesn't hurt her rights so much
because she really doesn't have that much use of the land immediately
around it, and B, to give her that land, which she doesn't
really even need so much, would jeopardize my ownership of the actual
tree itself. So in that type of a trade case where the
land is really necessary for the survival of the tree and it's
not really usable for her, we're going to assume that in that
case, right, I retain, I retain those rights for myself. Okay, so
in that case, כמשחי בארעא, kamchishi be'ara, that it's damaging the land,
so in the way it is, I mean, it wouldn't damage it
if you were to uproot it, but in the way it is,
it's damaging, שיורי שייר, shiurei shayer, then I must retain it for
myself, דלאו הכי לימא ליה אוקי אילנך וזיל, delav hachi leima leh
uki ilnach vezil, because otherwise, giving it to Jenna would actually undermine
my actual ownership of the tree itself. That's number one. Now,
now, מכר אילנות ושייר קרקע לפניו. machar ilanot veshayer karka lefanav. Now,
let's say it's the flip.
Oh, and although this is really not stuff for the third פרק,
we're only introducing it because we dealt before with the competing, with
the competing חזקות chazakot of David and Jenna, but we're going to
maybe circle back around to that. Now, let's say מכר אילנות ושייר
קרקע לפניו. machar ilanot veshayer karka lefanav.
Let's say it's the reverse. I sold, I sold David here, who's
interested in the trees, I sold him the trees, and I kept
the land for myself. Okay, so I did not divest myself of
the land. How much land does David own with the trees or
not? So the גמרא Gemara says like this, פלוגתא דרבי עקיבא ורבנן.
plugta deRabbi Akiva veRabbanan. So that's the straight debate of רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva, and the רבנן Rabbanan of בעין יפה be'ayin yafa or
בעין רעה. be'ayin ra'a. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva דאמר מוכר בעין יפה
מוכר, de'amar mocher be'ayin yafa mocher, אית ליה. it leh. רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva that says you sell with a generous eye, you have,
David has land. Now again, the question here is isn't that the
classic debate of, you know, the classic teaching of two trees, you
don't have land, three trees, you do have land? So תוספות Tosafot
and the רשב"ם Rashbam try to fit this in, but they basically
say, well, three trees everybody agrees you have land. Here the question
is two trees. And here the גמרא saying is that even according
to that, according to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, maybe like you have
at least some land. You don't have all the land between the
two trees, but you have some land, at least you have the
land maybe like directly underneath the trees, let's say. Okay, so the
amounts are not exactly specific. But nevertheless, the basic point is clear.
I sold David the trees and I still own the land. So
according to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva, that I'm generous, I'm giving David
some land to go with the trees, maybe just directly underneath it.
ורבנן, veRabbanan, according to the רבנן that we read what I'm giving
in very limited sense, לית ליה, leit leh, David only has the
trees, not the land. Now we're going to spell it out. רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva לית ליה? leit leh? Now, according to רבי עקיבא,
Rabbi Akiva, אית ליה, it leh, David gets the land. ואפילו רבי
זביד. ve'afilu Rabbi Zvid. Now we're tying it into רבי זביד Rabbi
Zvid and רב פפא. Rav Papa. Remember רבי זביד? Rabbi Zvid? רבי
זביד Rabbi Zvid said if David's working the trees and Jenna's working
the land, that David only has the trees, no land underneath it.
So now we're going to say, in that case, David could, I
could say that David could only have the trees, and at the
same time, if it's just me and David, we would say I
would give him the land. You got it? So David and Jenna
are both working a plot of land that used to be mine.
And then we say David's owning the trees does not represent ownership
of any part of the land. But if I just sold it
to David, then according to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva he would have
a part of the land. What's the difference? Let's take a look.
Okay, ואפילו רבי זביד דאמר אין לו. ve'afilu Rabbi Zvid de'amar ein
lo. When it's David and Jenna, David doesn't have any land that
goes with the trees. הני מילי גבי שני לקוחות. hanei milei gabei
shnei lekuchot. That's when there are two
purchasers, דאמר ליה, de'amar leh, that Jenna can say to David, "Hey,
look David, Dov was very clear. I have land and not trees,
and you have trees and not
land." כי היכי דלדידי לית לי באילנות, ki heichi delididi leit li
be'ilanot, the same way I don't get any trees, לדידך נמי לית
לך בארעא, ledidach nami leit lach be'ara, you don't get any land.
It was very clear what the split was. I get the land,
you get the trees. Okay, אבל הכא, aval hacha, wait a minute,
אבל הכא, aval hacha, but if it's just me and David, so
then, and I'm selling him my
trees, מוכר בעין יפה מוכר. mocher be'ayin yafa mocher. We'll say according
to רבי עקיבא that I'm generous, I give something with it. It's
assumed that together with the trees goes something that is necessary for
the ongoing survival of the tree and for the, you know, we
interpret it in generous terms. So when it's just between me and
David, we could say, like רבי עקיבא, we'll assume I gave him
what I gave him in generous terms. But when I'm explicit and
I'm saying I'm giving the land to one person and the trees
to the other, then there's not a question of generous. Any generosity
to David is going to hurt Jenna. So if I'm generous on
my account, it's going to hurt. But in this case, it's not
about being generous or not generous, it's about how did I divide
it? So Jenna's saying, "It's very clear how he divided it, I
get land and not trees." And you get land, I mean I
get land and not trees and you get trees and not land.
Yes.
Is it a מחלוקת machloket about how explicit you say something בפירוש
befeirush or simply the different set of assumptions when it's split between
two people as opposed to three people?
What מחלוקת? machloket? מוכר בעין יפה מוכר? mocher be'ayin yafa mocher? No,
it's a question...
No, it's like Dov sold to David and the land to Jenna.
Right. So it's a different... is it because... and so the land
goes all the way up to the trees. Right. The tree buyer
doesn't get any land.
Actually, the land goes under the trees.
Fine, but is that because you... is that because you have made
it explicit? I'm selling her all the trees.
Yeah. Well, that's the question. You haven't made it explicit. If you
made it explicit, there wouldn't be a debate. The question is that
there's room for interpretation and what should be our... our, you know,
sort of heuristics for interpretation in these legal debates?
But couldn't it be a different set of assumptions if you're selling
it just to one person?
There is! That's exactly what we just said. There is a different
set. That's exactly what the גמרא just said. But why? Why? Because
in one case we can... what do you mean? We could say...
we're going to say, using רבי עקיבא's language, we're going to assume
that a seller is generous. If you're taking money for it, you're
going to be a nice guy, you're going to give him like
the stuff that he needs to go with it. Okay, you're generous...
you're willing to give up... Fine, but here it's not a question
of generosity. I gave... I sold everything to David and to Jenna.
It's a question of how it gets divided between those. So using
a concept of generosity is irrelevant. Generous to David is hurtful to
Jenna.
The concept of generosity is an irrelevant... is an irrelevant concept when
you've totally divested yourself of the property.
But same thing with selling to one person.
No, that's not true.
Why? You just drew the...
I'm generous... generous means on your own account, you give up on
your... on your own benefit for somebody else. So that's relevant when
it's just you and the buyer.
But here you're giving up your whole benefit.
It's a question of who am I going to be generous to,
me on behalf of David, right? Like...
I got to think about it.
Okay. So now the גמרא says like this.
Okay. So... okay. Now, moving on.
לרבנן לית ליה. lerabbanan leit lei. Now, according to the רבנן who
says מוכר בעין רעה מוכר, mocher be'ayin ra'a mocher, so if I
just sold it to David, then he would not get any land.
Maybe not even the land directly underneath. ואפילו רב פפא דאמר יש
לו, ve'afilu Rav Pappa de'amar yeish lo, even according to רב פפא
Rav Pappa that says that when David and Jenna are equally being
מחזיק machzik in the land, David has a claim to some of
the land, we assume land went with the trees, so why there
does David have the land with the trees and when it's just
me and David he doesn't? הני מילי גבי שני לקוחות. hanei milei
gabei shenei lekuchot.
That's when there are two purchasers. So that's when you could say
the flip. In that case, I've... I'm not... if it's just me
and David, I'm going to hold back the maximum amount for myself.
And if I said trees, I just sold him trees. מוכר בעין
רעה מוכר. mocher be'ayin ra'a mocher. I'm totally self-interested here. But once
I'm fully divesting myself of the property, there's no benefit for me
to... so then it's not about what I'm holding back for myself.
So maybe I made a more equal division between David and Jenna.
Isn't this the point of both opinions of רב פפא Rav Pappa
too, two is different than one?
Right. הני... hanei... exactly. הני מילי גבי שני לקוחות דאמרי ליה כי
היכי דלדידך זבין בעין יפה, hanei milei gabei shenei lekuchot de'amrei lei
k'heichi delidach zavin be'ayin yafa, because David says to Jenna, "Look Jenna,
the same way Dov was generous to you..." Now how was Dov
generous to Jenna? I said קרקע, karka, I gave her קרקע. karka.
So what the רשב"ם Rashbam says is, is that let's face it,
you know, this is why real estate is like different than anything
that's not land. Land, like, lasts forever. Okay? And if you get
land, that means that, you know, you plant something now and it
doesn't survive and then you'll plant something ten years from now and
you'll have it for a hundred years. So the same way he
gave you land that's going to be like a real forever possession,
he also... we should assume didn't just give me trees. Presumably, he
also gave me some of the land that goes with the trees
so that I get something permanent out of it. כי היכי דלדידך
זבין בעין יפה לדידי נמי זבין בעין יפה. k'heichi delidach zavin be'ayin
yafa ledidi nami zavin be'ayin yafa.
So David says, "Yeah, you know, whatever, you got land, I should
assume that I get a little something permanent here." Okay. אבל הכא
מוכר בעין רעה מוכר. aval hacha mocher be'ayin ra'a mocher.
But if it's just between me and Dov, then we'll assume that
Dov held back for himself the maximum amount. Okay? So the point
is when it's just me and one buyer, we can either say
I'm as generous as possible, not as possible, but there's some generosity
to the buyer, or we could say I'm totally... I'm total self-interest,
I hold back for myself the maximum. But when I divest myself
of the property and it's between how did it get split, there
is nothing to do with עין יפה ayin yafa and עין רעה.
ayin ra'a. It has to do with how do we interpret how
that division took place. Do we assume all land and, you know,
land and not trees, trees and not land? Or do we assume
I would want to give each person something a little permanent? So
we should assume that David got some land to go with it.
So that's the debate between רב and רב פפא, Rav Pappa, but
it's a completely different חשבון cheshbon than when it's one buyer and
one seller where questions about generosity or lack of generosity are relevant
factors. Okay, so now the גמרא says like this.
Now we shift... switch gears.
Now, אמר נהרדעי, amar Naharda'ei, says נהרדעי, Naharda'ei, אכלן רצופין אין לו
חזקה. achlan retzufin ein lo chazaka.
If somebody ate dates that was like packed in, there's no חזקה.
chazakah It was all... now... now רצופין retzufin could sound like continuous,
like three continuous... years. And I thought the years are supposed to
be continuous. But what the רשב"ם Rashbam says what it means is
it's going back to, you know, to this idea here of the
tree of the ten trees to the בית סאה. beis se'ah. So
if there were more than ten trees to the בית סאה, beis
se'ah, it was really packed in, okay, it would not be a
חזקה. chazakah Why? Because...
And even if you did one line one year, one line another
year?
No, you did everything. Okay, because in that type of a case
now presumably it would be a חזקה chazakah on the trees but
it wouldn't be a חזקה chazakah on the קרקע. karka. Because in
that case since that's seen as like not a normal distribution so
now you could say all the more that they need more land,
but no, but we basically say like this is not, this is
not a permanent state, okay? This is a type of people don't
leave like an orchard things that's packed like this.
Okay. But you keep the trees? They keep the trees?
No, but but you don't get the land that goes with it,
okay? Land that goes with it is a concept of like an
orchard, you've got land and you've got the trees growing in the
land and it's set up in this, you know, and it's distributed
in the right amount of way that's going to make it a
successful type of a thing. If you've got these tightly packed trees,
then we assume that ownership of the trees doesn't suggest the same
type of ownership of the land.
I don't understand that logic. They said they're going to have to
uproot them.
Yeah, he said they're going to have to uproot them.
Okay, so so these are like mature trees, he's going to come
and like knock down his trees?
No, but it's the same thing when you're planting trees, you like
you plant more than then you...
Right, it's like a nursery
of trees, it's like a nursery of trees.
Right, that's what the רשב"ם Rashbam actually says. He says exactly that,
that when you start trees you plant a lot in in close
together and then you uproot them and you replant them more spread
out. So this is not a... what?
And that's not even what I think you you just...
it's like a nursery.
Oh you're just pruning... oh you just cut them down and then
you use the wood and then you leave the rest for whatever,
right.
At least what he's describing is a nursery, right? So when you
when you go to buy a tree, right, you have a field
of of small baby trees, right? And and they grow to be
the size like those trees that are on the way, right, trees
so they grow them packed,
right, and then they uproot them and they replant them.
Oh, cool. Exactly. And so the implication is is that you're if
you're in that kind of field that is that tight together that
means that...
Right, it's not a permanent setup. Right, the field is like a
temporary, maybe that's a helpful way of thinking about it. The field
is like a temporary holding container for the trees and it's not
an ongoing relationship of the field and the trees and they're growing
there long term. Right, so a חזקה chazakah on the tree is
not therefore a meaningful חזקה chazakah on the land. Okay. So that's
what he says. Okay. So he says okay, so אכלן רצופין אין
לו חזקה. achlan retzupin ein lo chazakah. So if they're packed in,
it's not a חזקה chazakah because you're ultimately going to replant them
and it's not like a reasonable set a long term setup here.
So מתקיף לה רבא maskif la Rava so Rava said אלא מעתה
ela me'ata האי משרא דאספסתא hai mishra d'aspasta so if that's true
a certain plot of אספסתא. aspasta. What is אספסתא aspasta again? Fodder,
not fodder, what is it? What does it say?
I forgot to look it up. It's some type of an animal
food.
Alfalfa. Alfalfa. Oh alfalfa. Okay, so if you've got some like plot
of alfalfa, במאי קני לה? be-mai kani-la? How could you be קונה
koneh it? Now why does it mean because the רשב"ם Rashbam says,
the רשב"ם says you always pack it in and then you replant
it or whatever, how are you supposed to do a קניין kinyan
if that's actually what you've got going? So how are you supposed
to do like a חזקה chazakah if that's the reality, like or
you could say let's say I went ahead and I bought I
bought David's nursery here and he had the stuff packed in and
I bought it with the land, how am I supposed to do
a חזקה chazakah in that scenario? So it says אלא אמר רבא
אכלן רצופין אין לו קרקע. ela amar Rava achlan retzupin ein lo
karka. Okay, so
actually up I jumped ahead. First you see I was already anticipating
you know reading in the end answer. So fine it would be
a חזקה chazakah on the actual trees,
you know it would be a חזקה chazakah on the actual alfalfa
but it wouldn't be a חזקה on the קרקע karka underneath which
still which still doesn't answer the question and if I bought the
קרקע karka underneath how would I do a חזקה on that? So
I don't exactly know the answer.
Okay, be careful of your שטר. What? Yeah they should be careful
of your שטר.
Yeah I have to be careful with my שטר. Yeah.
I don't understand how can you compare these little sapling trees that
are obviously going to be uprooted so it's just like a holding
place to any type of of small produce.
The רשב"ם says, the רשב"ם yeah I don't so the רשב"ם says
that explicitly. The רשב"ם says I don't understand the comparison. In this
case it's דרכו darko to grow this way, this case it's not
דרכו darko to grow this way. So then he suggests that maybe
with this alfalfa as well after it starts growing you uproot it
and spread it out, I don't know if that's true. Anyway the
רשב"ם points out it's not a good analogy. Anyway bottom line is
the חזקה works on the tree not on the land because it's
not a long term relationship with the trees and the land. Of
course how do you do a חזקה on the land is not
clear. All right now let's keep on going. The Gemara says אמר
רב זירא כתנאי. amar Rav Zeira ke-tannai. This issue of if something's
going to be uprooted do we look at it as like it's
there or it's not there and how do we look at the
land related to it is tied to a debate of תנאים. tannaim.
כרם שנטעו kerem she-nat'u Two, ah there you go Arty, exactly what
you said: כרם שניטוע פחות מארבע אמות. Kerem shenitua pachos me'arba amos.
You've got the—normally by the vines, you would have four אמות amos
between
each—what's it called—row, okay? But you packed in your vineyard, and the
space between the rows is less than four אמות. amos. So the
הלכה halacha is רבי שמעון אומר אינו כרם, Rabbi Shimon omer eino
kerem, it's not a vineyard. Now what's the relevance for it being
a vineyard? So תוספות Tosafot says, first of all, there's a question
about כלאים; kilayim; you have to stay more away from a vineyard
than you have to stay away from a single vine. Number two
is, he says, תוספות Tosafot has a nice נפקא מינא nafka mina
for the הלכה halacha of אשר נטע כרם ולא חללו, asher nata
kerem v'lo chilalo, that after somebody plants a vineyard, they don't have
to go to war for the first year. So if your vineyard
is too packed in, it doesn't count as a vineyard. Okay, so
a normal way you need a certain amount of space and spread
out for it to be considered to be like a viable long-term
setup.
Okay, other things too. So וחכמים אומרים הרי זה כרם. v'Chachamim omrim
harei zeh kerem. So no, even if it's too packed in, we
still look at it as viable. Why? רואים את האמצעיים כאילו אינם,
Ro'im es ha'emtza'im k'ilu einam, because you look at the middle vines,
you look at it as like those middle vines are uprooted and
don't exist, and if you took out the middle vines—you know, the
odd ones—so we would. That's why we said it's a debate of
תנאים. tannaim. So according to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, he says the
way it currently is, you've got to uproot something, then it's not
connected to the ground it's in. And the חכמים say no, some
of it is going to get uprooted, but some of it will
remain and it is connected to the ground it is in. It
is a vineyard and in this case maybe it would be a
חזקה to the land even though some will be uprooted, it won't
all be uprooted. Okay,
let's just read one more sentence. אמרי נהרדעי, Amri Neharde'ei, says נהרדעי,
Neharde'ei, האי מאן דזבין דיקלא לחבריה—this Hai man d'zavin dikla l'chaverei is
very much tied into exactly what we were discussing before—I sold the
palm tree to David. קני ליה, Kani lei, David gets the palm
tree משפולי
עד תהומא, mishipulei ad tehoma, from the edge of this ground to
the very depths. He gets all of the ground rights all the
way down to the very depths. Now the question is: one minute,
isn't that exactly based on the debate of עין רעה, ayin ra'ah,
עין יפה? ayin yafah? Does he get the land? Does he not
get the land? So some want to say yes, it is based
on the debate. Some say even if what it's saying is that
David doesn't own the land, what it's saying is that while he
has the palm tree, I am not allowed to dig underneath it,
even a hundred feet underneath it. David's got his palm tree. Why
can't you? Because that's his right. He doesn't own it, he doesn't
own it, okay? David has the palm tree, he has like a
lease essentially. He has rights to use the land even if he
doesn't own it. Those rights prevent me from digging a tunnel underneath
it even a hundred אמות amos deep underneath it. Okay, because he
has the rights—so either he owns it directly going down or he
has the rights directly going down all the way to the bottom.
Okay, that's how that's read.
And so we will—let me just see—wait a minute, okay you know
what, we'll end there. We will pick up with that discussion tomorrow.